<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Zander Gordan</title>
<link>https://www.zandergordan.com/</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.zandergordan.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Zander Gordan&#39;s personal blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.555</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>President’s Day Update</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/Presidents day 2025.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Well, despite rumors to the contrary, the blog lives on in 2025.</p>
<p>I continue to reside in Pinellas County, Florida, and despite attempts to escape it does appear at this point that this arrangement will continue into the foreseeable future, however short that may have now become. In any case I am presently enjoying a rare cool evening, with the promise of more to come soon, so I can pretend for a moment that the long Summer is not so menacingly imminent.</p>
<p>The economics career remains presently unchanged, I am a full time researcher moonlighting as an educator. I am thinking that the blog may become an outlet for some pedagogical material, since I simply have nowhere better to put such material.</p>
<p>Musically, I have been turning away from the DAW (Bitwig) lately in favor of practicing an instrument: the <a href="https://www.rogerlinndesign.com/linnstrument">Linnstrument</a>. Piano keyboard meets 8 string bass guitar, I am having a lot of fun with it, and have been more consistent in practicing than I ever was able to be with the keyboard. An underrated feature is that it accommodates a strap to be worn like a guitar, which for some reason makes me much more inclined to use it.</p>
<p>Economic uncertainty has been deterring me from booking travel aside from work travel, though Hannah has some trips in the works. As things firm up over the next few months, so may our travel agenda. So far we are on a 2 year streak with Transatlantic trips, hopefully we can make it a third.</p>
<p>I may have finally managed to become a morning person again, which is what you really ought to be when you live a short walk from brilliant sunrise views.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/Presidents day 2025.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New EP Out Now</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/musicstuff/someone or something.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I am releasing some tracks produced throughout the course of this year, some were done on my old Ableton setup and some on the new Bitwig setup, I believe all include the analog Eurorack gear I got in Scotland on the Honeymoon. Available now on Soundcloud and eventually on other streaming platforms as well.</p>
<p>By the way I am taking keyboard lessons now and hope to produce some stuff more in the Western 12TET tradition, and also to collaborate more instead of doing this all at my home studio alone.</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="300" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" allow="autoplay" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/playlists/1871656904&amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;show_teaser=true&amp;visual=true"></iframe><div style="font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;"><a href="https://soundcloud.com/zandergordan" title="Zander Gordan" target="_blank" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;">Zander Gordan</a> · <a href="https://soundcloud.com/zandergordan/sets/someone-or-something-is-ringing-the-bell" title="Someone Or Something Is Ringing The Bell" target="_blank" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;">Someone Or Something Is Ringing The Bell</a></div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/musicstuff/someone or something.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I Switched to Bitwig</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/musicstuff/bitwig switch.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/musicstuff/auto organ patch.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">My first Bitwig Grid Patch</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With Labor day fast approaching I thought it was time to post again. Life has gone on mostly smoothly, I am on the job market which is always fun, and in the meantime I have made some fun adjustments. I posted <a href="https://zandergordan.com/posts/maxmsp/beginnings-with-max.html">previously</a> about trying to learn Max/MSP, and I struggled quite a bit with this endeavor. I had heard of Bitwig and it’s Grid, and eventually decided to sell my Push and give it a try. I’m so glad I did!</p>
<p>My early efforts with Bitwig revolved around integrating my fledlging hardware modular setup with the Grid, which is straightfoward and rewarding to do. But this weekend I finally decided to tackle a more ambitious project, which I originally was trying to do in Max/MSP. It is a synth patch that I refer to as an “Auto Tremolo MPE Organ.” It incorporates 3 dimensions of MPE sensitivity per voice, X Y and Z. X maps to pitch as usual, and Z to overall volume, but Y deviates from its normal use as a “timbre” control and instead affects the rate of an LFO that is hooked into the VCA to give a Tremolo effect. Below is a demo of what is possible with this configuration:</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="300" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" allow="autoplay" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/1899699066%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-5LlfBk93vzf&amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;show_teaser=true&amp;visual=true"></iframe><div style="font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;"><a href="https://soundcloud.com/zandergordan" title="Zander Gordan" target="_blank" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;">Zander Gordan</a> · <a href="https://soundcloud.com/zandergordan/auto-organ-demo-2024-08-18-1735/s-5LlfBk93vzf" title="Auto Organ Demo 2024 - 08 - 18 1735" target="_blank" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;">Auto Organ Demo 2024 - 08 - 18 1735</a></div>
<p>Note that both the Y and Z dimensions of control are affecting volume. In other words, the effect I achieve here could theoretically be achieved by a skilled player simply manipulating the Z dimension in a rhythmic fashion. But I doubt I personally could achieve the sound that I do with this configuration without the LFO-enabled auto tremolo. And there is still some room to route the Y and Z controls to additional destinations to achieve some deeper control over tone for an even more expressive patch. But before going down that route I simply want to explore what is possible compositionally, the demo above is just a black key jam that I threw together with minimal effort. Below is the preset in case anyone ever wants to try it themselves.</p>
<p><a href="MPE Auto Tremolo Organ.bwpreset">Download Preset</a></p>
<p>Overall I can not thank the Bitwig team enough for their efforts in creating this intuitive virtual modular environment, I really struggle to express how much simpler it was to achieve my vision with this system compared to my struggles earlier trying to learn Max/MSP. I am sure Max has it’s place, especially in providing greater flexibility for full-time music technologists, but as a hobbyist finding time for music around the demands of a full time career I think the Grid is truly brilliant in its simplicity and accessibility.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>technology</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/musicstuff/bitwig switch.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weekend Update #4</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/WU 4.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Happy Memorial Day!</p>
<p>There is nothing much to report around here. In many places throughout America today will mark the “start of Summer”, but here in Pinellas County the long Summer has already begun some weeks ago, and I do not expect reprieve until, optimistically, Halloween.</p>
<p>Amid the heat, I have mostly been sheltering inside, though we did manage to get a little sunburnt earlier this weekend. The twilight hours should in principle be quite nice right now, were it not for the bugs. Though we in any case try to enjoy them a bit.</p>
<p>All creative pursuits except dancing have been put on the backburner for now, but we will see if the Summer does not provide some opportunities to return to them.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/WU 4.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weekend Update #3</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/WU 3.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/DSC02039.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Me in Iceland</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Most notably, we have returned from Iceland. The hot dogs are nothing special despite supposedly containing some amount of lamb, but represent an oasis of value in an otherwise high COL country: I had 5 over 6 days. Early April is a “shoulder season” but I thought it was ideal in providing the “ice” in Iceland while still being easy to navigate. Hannah wants to go back in Summer, but I fear the crowds.</p>
<p>My fitness routine has shifted to consisting almost entirely of freestyle dance for cardio and functional strength, while traditional strength training has been relegated to “someday.” The scale approves of the shift but my legs are in a perpetual state of soreness.</p>
<p>The Bible study has taken a backseat to Norse mythology, which I picked up a couple books on while in the Keflavik airport on the way home from Iceland. I consider these essentially fungible “wisdom literature” sources. I had not realized what a selected subsample of the myths were preserved, relative to the Greek ones that I studied in high school.</p>
<p>There is unfortunately no news in regard to music; the next likely release is DFO vol 2. Max/MSP progress has ground to a halt, but in the meantime I have developed concrete ideas I want to execute on that should ultimately motivate me to resume that course of study.</p>
<p>I have a new-found appreciation of candlelight.</p>
<p>Everton secured safety some weeks ago. Tomorrow they have the potential to play spoiler if Man City can not pull out a win, but I probably can not even be bothered to watch. It is too early to say how the Braves season looks, but the fact they currently trail the Phillies is cause for significant distress in our household. I do not follow FSU off-season developments but hopefully things are going well, as I understand it the rules are now changed so that an ACC championship will be sufficient to put us in the expanded playoffs, regardless of the opinions of any committee.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/WU 3.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weekend Update #2</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/WU 2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Happy St.&nbsp;Patrick’s day, for another 3 hours at least. As I begin writing, Atlanta United is about to wrap up at 2-0 victory over Orlando, getting a healthy start to the 2024 campaign.</p>
<p>The MLB season will begin on Tuesday, with a break from tradition as the Dodgers and Padres play a 2 game series in Korea, before Opening Day. Hannah will be waking up to watch these games at 6am eastern, I will have to make a game-time decision as to whether I am willing to give up my beauty sleep.</p>
<p>I finished reading my last great book some time ago, which was the Briggs translation of War and Peace. I’ve decided to embark on a new literary undertaking, which is to get a study bible (HarperCollins) and some other related works and begin familiarizing myself with the Christian tradition. This obviously is a long-term endeavor, and in my opinion not likely to be terribly rewarding on its own, and so my plan is to intersperse this learning with revisiting some of the classics already familiar to me, including especially Shakespeare, and the American Transcendentalists, and to try to appreciate aspects of these works which I may have not when I read them in High School with little to no familiarity with the Bible.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>sports</category>
  <category>literature</category>
  <category>religion</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/WU 2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Put Your Money Where Your Mouth Is: Built For the Postseason Edition</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/MLB/MLB 2024 Season Odds.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The 2024 MLB season is almost underway, and oddsmakers have set their predictions for the season.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(tidyverse)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr">
<pre><code>── Attaching core tidyverse packages ──────────────────────── tidyverse 2.0.0 ──
✔ dplyr     1.1.4     ✔ readr     2.1.4
✔ forcats   1.0.0     ✔ stringr   1.5.1
✔ ggplot2   3.4.4     ✔ tibble    3.2.1
✔ lubridate 1.9.3     ✔ tidyr     1.3.0
✔ purrr     1.0.2     
── Conflicts ────────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse_conflicts() ──
✖ dplyr::filter() masks stats::filter()
✖ dplyr::lag()    masks stats::lag()
ℹ Use the conflicted package (&lt;http://conflicted.r-lib.org/&gt;) to force all conflicts to become errors</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb3-1">df <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">read_csv</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"2024seasonOdds.csv"</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr">
<pre><code>Warning: One or more parsing issues, call `problems()` on your data frame for details,
e.g.:
  dat &lt;- vroom(...)
  problems(dat)</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr">
<pre><code>Rows: 30 Columns: 3
── Column specification ────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
Delimiter: ","
chr (1): team
dbl (1): Ewins
num (1): OddsWS

ℹ Use `spec()` to retrieve the full column specification for this data.
ℹ Specify the column types or set `show_col_types = FALSE` to quiet this message.</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb6-1">df</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code># A tibble: 30 × 3
   team      Ewins OddsWS
   &lt;chr&gt;     &lt;dbl&gt;  &lt;dbl&gt;
 1 Dodgers   104.     320
 2 Braves    102.     450
 3 Astros     93.5    700
 4 Yankees    91.5    950
 5 Phillies   89.5   1500
 6 Orioles    89.5   1400
 7 Rangers    88.5   1400
 8 Mariners   87.5   2000
 9 Twins      87.5   2100
10 Blue Jays  86.5   1800
# ℹ 20 more rows</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<p>I have collected the odds from Fanduel on each MLB team’s over/under for total regular season wins, and the odds of the team winning the world series. How do these correlate?</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb8" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb8-1">df <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb8-2">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ggplot</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> Ewins, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">y =</span> OddsWS)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb8-3">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">geom_point</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">scale_y_log10</span>()</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/MLB/MLB-2024-Season-Odds_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>It seems that there is pretty much a log-linear inverse relationship between expected win total (technically an over under is not the same thing as an expected value, but I will use the terms interchangeably) and your winnings from betting the team to win the world series. Notably, for the worst teams, you do not win as much for betting on them as you might expect, no doubt the oddsmakers want to limit their potential downside from those who are attracted to the most outrageous bets.</p>
<p>I think it may be useful also to convert the odds to break-even win probabilities:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb9" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb9-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(plotly)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr">
<pre><code>
Attaching package: 'plotly'</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr">
<pre><code>The following object is masked from 'package:ggplot2':

    last_plot</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr">
<pre><code>The following object is masked from 'package:stats':

    filter</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr">
<pre><code>The following object is masked from 'package:graphics':

    layout</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb14" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb14-1">df <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> df <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb14-2">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mutate</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">pWS =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">100</span> <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span> (<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">100</span> <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> OddsWS),</span>
<span id="cb14-3">         <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">pWS =</span> pWS <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sum</span>(pWS))</span>
<span id="cb14-4"></span>
<span id="cb14-5"></span>
<span id="cb14-6">p <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> df <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb14-7">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ggplot</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> Ewins, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">y =</span> pWS, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">text =</span> team)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb14-8">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">geom_point</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">scale_y_log10</span>() </span>
<span id="cb14-9"></span>
<span id="cb14-10"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ggplotly</span>(p)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="plotly html-widget html-fill-item" id="htmlwidget-b3e728e88f3a64cf471f" style="width:100%;height:464px;"></div>
<script type="application/json" data-for="htmlwidget-b3e728e88f3a64cf471f">{"x":{"data":[{"x":[103.5,101.5,93.5,91.5,89.5,89.5,88.5,87.5,87.5,86.5,84.5,84.5,83.5,83.5,83.5,82.5,81.5,80.5,80.5,79.5,77.5,77.5,76.5,75.5,73.5,72.5,66.5,60.5,59.5,57.5],"y":[-0.72784684729779137,-0.8449602463941347,-1.0076875438918345,-1.125786855969829,-1.3087175395558157,-1.280688815955572,-1.280688815955572,-1.4268168516338102,-1.4470202377220971,-1.3833511578527198,-1.5959592507341636,-1.5959592507341636,-1.7173814136196264,-1.6609000576671782,-1.7947936369284045,-1.8121677329978272,-1.8899273919106578,-1.8121677329978272,-1.9558559056189662,-1.8899273919106578,-2.0636389492209846,-1.8899273919106578,-2.0636389492209846,-2.4077936143203797,-2.2835745041930604,-2.3622761317690752,-2.5042712783809291,-2.5042712783809291,-2.8044352827671366,-2.8044352827671366],"text":["Ewins: 103.5<br />pWS: 0.187134195<br />Dodgers","Ewins: 101.5<br />pWS: 0.142902476<br />Braves","Ewins:  93.5<br />pWS: 0.098245452<br />Astros","Ewins:  91.5<br />pWS: 0.074853678<br />Yankees","Ewins:  89.5<br />pWS: 0.049122726<br />Phillies","Ewins:  89.5<br />pWS: 0.052397575<br />Orioles","Ewins:  88.5<br />pWS: 0.052397575<br />Rangers","Ewins:  87.5<br />pWS: 0.037426839<br />Mariners","Ewins:  87.5<br />pWS: 0.035725619<br />Twins","Ewins:  86.5<br />pWS: 0.041366506<br />Blue Jays","Ewins:  84.5<br />pWS: 0.025353665<br />Rays","Ewins:  84.5<br />pWS: 0.025353665<br />Cardinals","Ewins:  83.5<br />pWS: 0.019169844<br />Diamondbacks","Ewins:  83.5<br />pWS: 0.021832323<br />Cubs","Ewins:  83.5<br />pWS: 0.016040074<br />Padres","Ewins:  82.5<br />pWS: 0.015411051<br />Reds","Ewins:  81.5<br />pWS: 0.012884649<br />Giants","Ewins:  80.5<br />pWS: 0.015411051<br />Mets","Ewins:  80.5<br />pWS: 0.011069910<br />Tigers","Ewins:  79.5<br />pWS: 0.012884649<br />Guardians","Ewins:  77.5<br />pWS: 0.008636963<br />Marlins","Ewins:  77.5<br />pWS: 0.012884649<br />Red Sox","Ewins:  76.5<br />pWS: 0.008636963<br />Brewers","Ewins:  75.5<br />pWS: 0.003910267<br />Pirates","Ewins:  73.5<br />pWS: 0.005205057<br />Royals","Ewins:  72.5<br />pWS: 0.004342340<br />Angels","Ewins:  66.5<br />pWS: 0.003131329<br />Nationals","Ewins:  60.5<br />pWS: 0.003131329<br />White Sox","Ewins:  59.5<br />pWS: 0.001568790<br />Rockies","Ewins:  57.5<br />pWS: 0.001568790<br />Athletics"],"type":"scatter","mode":"markers","marker":{"autocolorscale":false,"color":"rgba(0,0,0,1)","opacity":1,"size":5.6692913385826778,"symbol":"circle","line":{"width":1.8897637795275593,"color":"rgba(0,0,0,1)"}},"hoveron":"points","showlegend":false,"xaxis":"x","yaxis":"y","hoverinfo":"text","frame":null}],"layout":{"margin":{"t":26.228310502283108,"r":7.3059360730593621,"b":40.182648401826498,"l":54.794520547945211},"plot_bgcolor":"rgba(235,235,235,1)","paper_bgcolor":"rgba(255,255,255,1)","font":{"color":"rgba(0,0,0,1)","family":"","size":14.611872146118724},"xaxis":{"domain":[0,1],"automargin":true,"type":"linear","autorange":false,"range":[55.200000000000003,105.8],"tickmode":"array","ticktext":["60","70","80","90","100"],"tickvals":[60,70,80,90,100],"categoryorder":"array","categoryarray":["60","70","80","90","100"],"nticks":null,"ticks":"outside","tickcolor":"rgba(51,51,51,1)","ticklen":3.6529680365296811,"tickwidth":0.66417600664176002,"showticklabels":true,"tickfont":{"color":"rgba(77,77,77,1)","family":"","size":11.68949771689498},"tickangle":-0,"showline":false,"linecolor":null,"linewidth":0,"showgrid":true,"gridcolor":"rgba(255,255,255,1)","gridwidth":0.66417600664176002,"zeroline":false,"anchor":"y","title":{"text":"Ewins","font":{"color":"rgba(0,0,0,1)","family":"","size":14.611872146118724}},"hoverformat":".2f"},"yaxis":{"domain":[0,1],"automargin":true,"type":"linear","autorange":false,"range":[-2.908264704540604,-0.62401742552432404],"tickmode":"array","ticktext":["0.003","0.010","0.030","0.100"],"tickvals":[-2.5228787452803374,-2,-1.5228787452803376,-1],"categoryorder":"array","categoryarray":["0.003","0.010","0.030","0.100"],"nticks":null,"ticks":"outside","tickcolor":"rgba(51,51,51,1)","ticklen":3.6529680365296811,"tickwidth":0.66417600664176002,"showticklabels":true,"tickfont":{"color":"rgba(77,77,77,1)","family":"","size":11.68949771689498},"tickangle":-0,"showline":false,"linecolor":null,"linewidth":0,"showgrid":true,"gridcolor":"rgba(255,255,255,1)","gridwidth":0.66417600664176002,"zeroline":false,"anchor":"x","title":{"text":"pWS","font":{"color":"rgba(0,0,0,1)","family":"","size":14.611872146118724}},"hoverformat":".2f"},"shapes":[{"type":"rect","fillcolor":null,"line":{"color":null,"width":0,"linetype":[]},"yref":"paper","xref":"paper","x0":0,"x1":1,"y0":0,"y1":1}],"showlegend":false,"legend":{"bgcolor":"rgba(255,255,255,1)","bordercolor":"transparent","borderwidth":1.8897637795275593,"font":{"color":"rgba(0,0,0,1)","family":"","size":11.68949771689498}},"hovermode":"closest","barmode":"relative"},"config":{"doubleClick":"reset","modeBarButtonsToAdd":["hoverclosest","hovercompare"],"showSendToCloud":false},"source":"A","attrs":{"74c371a2e1da":{"x":{},"y":{},"text":{},"type":"scatter"}},"cur_data":"74c371a2e1da","visdat":{"74c371a2e1da":["function (y) ","x"]},"highlight":{"on":"plotly_click","persistent":false,"dynamic":false,"selectize":false,"opacityDim":0.20000000000000001,"selected":{"opacity":1},"debounce":0},"shinyEvents":["plotly_hover","plotly_click","plotly_selected","plotly_relayout","plotly_brushed","plotly_brushing","plotly_clickannotation","plotly_doubleclick","plotly_deselect","plotly_afterplot","plotly_sunburstclick"],"base_url":"https://plot.ly"},"evals":[],"jsHooks":[]}</script>
</div>
</div>
<p>Now we get a positive log-linear relationship, which is more intuitive. I will note that there really are not any extreme off-diagonal outliers here. A dot far up and to the left in this plot would represent a team “built for the playoffs”, that is having a much better chance of winning the World Series than their regular season projections would suggest. As far as Vegas is considered, there really are no such teams. The closest would be the Red Sox, with a 1.2% chance compared to the 0.8% chance of the Marlins, despite having the same expected wins 77.5 wins, or put another way the same chance of winning as the giants who have 81.5 expected wins.</p>
<p>So, are there any teams that are uniquely “built for the playoffs?” If you think there is, maybe you should bet on them to win it all. Otherwise, if “built for the playoffs” is just a verbose way of saying “good,” then maybe we should retire the phrase.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sports</category>
  <category>baseball</category>
  <category>math</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/MLB/MLB 2024 Season Odds.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>It Has Happened</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/maxmsp/success-with-ai.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/maxmsp/ai_screenshot_20240309.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>AI has provided me with useful results. It only took over a year. I tried several times earlier last year, and never found it very useful.</p>
<p>What is notable about the current success is that I was asking it for some very basic advice about using the programming language Max. Whereas my priory inquiries had been about relatively advanced economics or R programming, which the AI did not seem capable of helping with.</p>
<p>Overall I am still not as convinced of how groundbreaking this stuff is as some people are, but I see clearly now that it is a great boon for learners and pedagogy, assuming that it can be relied upon to know its own limitations. A significant improvement over the previous method of searching for help in this context: googling keywords and praying for a well written forum post.</p>
<p>And yes, the inquiry was in service of creating my very own first original Max patch: a simple clocked random sampler, the core logic for which is now complete. I now simply need to learn the Max4Live components necessary to flesh out a user interface and i/o that is compatible with the Push 3.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>programming</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/maxmsp/success-with-ai.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>(Re)Starting to Learn Max/MSP</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/maxmsp/beginnings-with-max.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/maxmsp/first_max_patch.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Zander’s First Max Patch in 2024</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This evening I am embarking on something which I have not seriously considered since 2020: learning a new programming language. At that time I decided to learn the R language since it was the data analysis tool of choice among my new coworkers at NOAA, now I am learning Max MSP because it appears to be the tool of choice for a lot of people making weird electronic music.</p>
<p>I have been aware of Max for a long time, since at least 2011 I think. I may have even experimented with it at some point in late high school or early college. And since returning to Ableton Live to make music over the past year or so, I have used Max For Live devices, especially in recent months to interface between Ableton and my eurorack rig. In fact, this is precisely my motivator for learning the language: I want to make Max4Live devices that will augment the possibilities of my Eurorack + Push setup, without having to get a bigger eurorack case and amassing a larger collection of modules.</p>
<p>I am happy to see that there is now what seems to be a great resource for someone in my position, in the form of a Kadenze course. As I recall, the information available online for learning Max back 10-15 years ago was not particularly accessible, or anyway that is how I remember feeling at the time.</p>
<p>It’s worth noting that yesterday evening I briefly looked into learning C++, with an eye to eventually using JUCE to do plugin development and learn DSP that way, but I think I am going to get a lot more fulfillment out of the limited time I have to devote to music stuff by going the Max route.</p>
<p>The screenshot above is from the first exercise of the Kadenze course, which is assembled step by step in the lesson videos, and the exercise is then to slightly modify the patch to change the behavior. It took me just a couple minutes to think of how to complete the exercise, and I learned a good bit in the process. Overall I am impressed with the pedagogy so far, and hope the rest of the class will be equally good.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>programming</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/maxmsp/beginnings-with-max.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>EBINLO Is Dead, Long Live EBINLO</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/ebinlo-dead/long-live.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I am now releasing music under the artist name Zander Gordan. The former name EBINLO was chosen at random, as something that could reasonably pass for a DJ/Producer moniker. Contrary to some suspicions, it was not an acronym. When I made the decision last year to make some music again for the first time in a long time, I was not ready to associate what I was doing with my own name and ego, so a disposable moniker was necessary for the sake of psychological distance. I am now more confident that this is something I intend to do for the long term, and it feels appropriate to release music going forward under my own name.</p>
<p>I am also switching to Soundcloud as my distributor for the time being, so my new tracks will be available there first before they are on Spotify et al.&nbsp;I just released a new track: I’m Sorry Babe But I Just Can’t Dance To This Chord Progression</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="300" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" allow="autoplay" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/1750267074&amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;show_teaser=true&amp;visual=true"></iframe><div style="font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;"><a href="https://soundcloud.com/zandergordan" title="Zander Gordan" target="_blank" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;">Zander Gordan</a> · <a href="https://soundcloud.com/zandergordan/sorry-babe-but-i-just-cant-dance-to-this-chord-progression" title="Sorry Babe But I Just Can't Dance To This Chord Progression" target="_blank" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;">Sorry Babe But I Just Can't Dance To This Chord Progression</a></div>
<p>It is my favorite little bit of modular mayhem yet: almost everything you hear in this track is the <a href="https://www.signalsounds.com/steady-state-fate-entity-ultra-perc-eurorack-percussion-module">SSF Ultra-Perc</a> being modulated 5 different ways, including at audio rates.</p>
<p>Here’s to many more releases to come!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>life</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/ebinlo-dead/long-live.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Put Your Money Where Your Mouth Is: Superbowl Conspiracy Edition</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/superbowl-conspiracy/put-your-money.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It is presently fashionable in some quarters to insist that today’s big game is rigged in favor of the Chiefs (the details do not bear repeating so I will leave it at that). With sports betting now legal in many jurisdictions across the US, I wonder what portion of people who hold this belief are interested in monetizing their insider knowledge.</p>
<p>I just checked my local sports betting app, and the odds ratios are 1.83 for the 49er’s and 2.00 for the Chiefs, meaning the 49ers are in fact slightly favored by Vegas, and the app is offering a double-or-nothing proposition for every dollar someone wagers on the Chiefs.</p>
<p>If you are 90+ percent sure that the game is rigged in favor of the Chiefs, what portion of your life savings should you be betting on this incredible chance to double your money instantly?</p>
<p>As a side note, I believe most betting operators have the home address of their customers, and perhaps even some other demographic data. I would love to see an analysis of how wagers for the Chiefs correlate at the voting precinct level with recent election results, among other things. But I do not think Vegas is known for being generous with their data, oh well…</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>sports</category>
  <category>politics</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/superbowl-conspiracy/put-your-money.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ode to the Keytar</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/keytar/ode.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<iframe src="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1IWFMi2ikK06W1stPUEl7rNqFqiXMNuAS/preview" width="640" height="480" allow="autoplay"></iframe>
<p>Today I am packing up my keytar, to ship it off to it’s buyer. This is in fact the second keytar I have owned, having sold the first one back in I believe 2017. I have fond memories of both models, this one a Korg RK-100S2, which has microKORG-esque presets, and I love the ergonomics of the keytar, allowing me to riff on a melody while walking around my house absent-mindedly.</p>
<p>But, unfortunately I just don’t think the keytar fits into my plans for the EBINLO project. I plan on using Eurorack sequencers to create the melodies for EBINLO songs, and frankly my keyboard skills were never all that impressive anyway.</p>
<p>I will at times miss the keytar, but in any case I think it will be best that I get used to using the pads on my Ableton Push for any melodic sequencing outside of the Eurorack; there’s just no need for a traditional keyboard in my current setup. As per my last post, I am down to just the modular and the Push, and I want to force myself to really focus on exploring that setup.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>life</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/keytar/ode.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>First Eurorack Case Built</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/eurorack-groovebox/case-complete.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/eurorack-groovebox/mantis.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Today I’ve finally finished doing something that I started last year: building out my first eurorack case. It started with the Moog Mother-32 and DFAM combo, which I got when I visited the Moog factory / flagship store during my bachelor party last year. I then added a few modules when I visited Scotland on the honeymoon and made a stop at <a href="https://www.signalsounds.com">Signal Sounds</a> in Glasgow. Since then I have made another order from Signal Sounds, and I asked my family for a couple modules for Christmas, and now I have the result.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.modulargrid.net/e/racks/view/2456186" class="uri">https://www.modulargrid.net/e/racks/view/2456186</a></p>
<p>In addition to the modular, I also picked up the Ableton Push 3 last year. I used to have a Push 2 but sold it years ago as I never used it. Earlier this week, I was thinking about selling the Push 3 for the same reason. But I’ve decided I’m going to unplug the Push from the computer and get used to doing everything in the standalone mode. I think the learning curve will be steep getting used to doing things on the Push, but it will ultimately be better than if I just keep using the keyboard and mouse for everything.</p>
<p>The Expert Sleepers ES-3 and ES-6 modules in the Eurorack connect to the Push through ADAT, and I use the Push as a mixer, as a sampler, for effects, and for LFO’s through the CV Tools add-on.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/eurorack-groovebox/music setup.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>So that’s the whole setup, and I think I will keep it this way probably at least through the early Summer, and try to make a few tracks with this configuration. Perhaps it is optimistic to think I can abstain from adding on to the eurorack for that long.</p>
<p>Here are a few snippets from me jamming on the modular (no Ableton except for mixing):</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" allow="autoplay" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/1722544707&amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;show_teaser=true"></iframe><div style="font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;"><a href="https://soundcloud.com/ebinlo" title="EBINLO" target="_blank" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;">EBINLO</a> · <a href="https://soundcloud.com/ebinlo/eurorack-jam-highlights-jan-19-2024" title="Eurorack Jam Highlights Jan 19 2024" target="_blank" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;">Eurorack Jam Highlights Jan 19 2024</a></div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>life</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/eurorack-groovebox/case-complete.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weekend Update #1</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/weekend-update.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Everton picks up a hard fought <a href="https://www.liverpoolecho.co.uk/sport/football/football-news/everton-aston-villa-score-highlights-28443636">point</a> over Villa, providing a little separation from the relegation zone. I remain optimistic the new stadium will debut as an EPL venue. UTFT.</p>
<p>Good news out of the Florida legislature’s first week in session, some bipartisan sanity on the outrageous “slavery benefited the slaves” history curriculum: <a href="https://floridaphoenix.com/2024/01/11/dems-gop-push-to-remove-language-about-slaves-skills-and-personal-benefit-in-fl-state-standards/">Florida Phoenix</a></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.bonnaroo.com">Bonnaroo</a> lineup is out, I am pleased especially with Sunday’s Four Tet and fred again.. inclusion.</p>
<p>Mike Norvell will <a href="https://www.tallahassee.com/story/sports/college/fsu/football/2024/01/12/mike-norvell-stays-fsu-football-coach-wont-replace-nick-saban-alabama/72142161007/">remain</a> as head coach for FSU, what a wonderful bit of news to emerge amongst the Alabama search for a Saban successor.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sports</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>policy</category>
  <category>florida</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/weekend-update-1/weekend-update.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Amend Those Teenage Labor Bills</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/teenage-labor/amend-those.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/teenage-labor/ff87b992-6c1b-497b-8584-258990c146ed_550x364.webp" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><a href="https://www.myfloridahouse.gov/Sections/Bills/billsdetail.aspx?BillId=78634">Florida HB 49 (2024)</a>&nbsp;should be amended to retain the restrictions on hours of work for 16 and 17 year olds, but clarify and expand the scope for existing exemptions granted by the schools. There should be a simple, objective process by which a high school student on track to graduate (ie 2.0 GPA, passing EOC's, etc.) can get a waiver to work without the hours restrictions, so long as their academic progress continues apace. Furthermore, schools should maintain a registry of students requesting and receiving such waivers, with such registry being shared with the FLDOE and academic partners for research purposes. In this way we can track the outcomes of students working extended hours, and advance the state of knowledge on the effect of teenage labor force participation on long run outcomes.</p>
<p>HB 49 seeks to change some of the labor laws for teenagers, perhaps most notably by lifting restrictions on the hours of work for 16 and 17 year olds, which according to the staff analysis of the bill (p9)&nbsp;includes the following restrictions:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Before 6:30 a.m. or after 11:00 p.m.</p></li>
<li><p>More than 8 hours in any one day when school is scheduled the following day.</p></li>
<li><p>When school is in session, more than 30 hours in any one week.</p></li>
<li><p>During school hours on any school day, if not enrolled in a career education program.</p></li>
<li><p>More than 6 consecutive days in any one week.</p></li>
<li><p>More than 4 hours continuously without an interval of at least 30 minutes for a meal period.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>One aspect of these restrictions which I have not seen discussed in the media&nbsp;is the various exemptions to them which already exist under current law. As per the same staff analysis, those exemptions include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Minors 16 and 17 years-of-age who have graduated from high school or received a high school equivalency diploma.</p></li>
<li><p>Minors who are within the compulsory school attendance age limit who hold a valid certificate of exemption issued by the school superintendent or his or her designee pursuant to the provisions of s. 1003.21(3), F.S.</p></li>
<li><p>Minors enrolled in a public educational institution who qualify on a hardship basis such as economic necessity or family emergency.</p>
<ul>
<li>Such determination must be made by the school superintendent or his or her designee, and a waiver of hours must be issued to the minor and the employer.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Children in domestic service in private homes, children employed by their parents, or pages in the Florida Legislature.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>As I see it, these existing exemptions reflect the fact that not all teenagers are the same, and a one-size-fits-all policy that places the same restrictions on the labor supply of all teenagers is not desirable. The first exemption, for students who graduate or get their GED early, seems especially reasonable to me. The second and third exemptions, in which waivers may be granted with the intervention of the superintendent or their designee, are the focus of my post. I have only been able to gather limited information about these waivers, a number of counties have webpages providing details about how these waivers may be obtained, including Escambia, Volusia, Brevard and Alachua.</p>
<p>It seems in these districts there is generally an administrative staff member who is responsible for signing off on these waivers, which require a significant amount of paperwork, and involve a subjective assessment by administrative staff as to whether granting the waiver is in the best interests of the students. Therefore, I can understand the desire, expressed in HB 49, to do away with these restrictions so that this waiver process is no longer needed. However, I think a smarter option is to streamline the process for obtaining a waiver, such that the waiver is granted automatically as long as a student is on track to graduate, meaning they are maintaining a 2.0 GPA, not be excessively tardy or absent, etc. If a students' grades dropped, the waiver would be automatically revoked, The advantages of streamlining the waiver system, as opposed to doing away with the restrictions entirely, are two-fold:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>It would ensure that students' education is not hampered by their work schedule. Those opposed to HB 49 imagine students working long hours or overnight shifts, coming in to school tired and not performing well in school, potentially even dropping out. By maintaining a waiver system tied to staying on track to graduate, we could avoid the worst case scenarios that might play out under a full repeal.</p></li>
<li><p>It would create a registry of students who are working without the hours restrictions. By sharing this registry with trusted research partners, and keeping track of students working under waivers through graduation and beyond, we could learn more about the effects of teenage labor force participation on these young people's lives.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>I view the second point as especially important. The fact is, we know very little about what is the best way for young people to be spending their time during crucial formative years as they transition to adulthood and enter the workforce, particularly given the rapidly changing nature of our economy. Personally, I think extensive participation in the labor force at a young age may be beneficial for some teenagers, especially those who might, for instance, go on to form their own businesses. In the media coverage surrounding HB 49, one 16 year old named Logan Schulenberger is quoted as being in favor of the bill lifting the hours restrictions. Logan apparently works as a martial arts instructor, and so if that is his path then all the better for him to get experience early and advance his career in that field.&nbsp;</p>
<p>For certain professions such as automotive technician, welder, farmer, etc. the schools operate vocational programs where students can earn school credits taking classes about their profession, and get work experience through an employer affiliated with the school, but these programs are limited in scope and not applicable to many students. While I certainly support expanding vocational education as an alternative to the college preparatory track which I think many agree has become oversaturated, having a waiver system for students to work full time schedules or flexible schedules while in school is another viable option for expanding the range of paths students may take as they transition into the workforce.</p>
<p>Only by keeping track of the students who avail themselves of these waivers, and seeing how things play out for them, can we learn more about what the actual effect of increased high school labor force participation is. HB 49 as written would not provide us with the opportunity to gather this valuable information, and additionally it would not provide any safeguards against extended working hours adversely impacting students' academic outcomes, which is why the bill should be amended before advancing any further in the 2024 session.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>policy</category>
  <category>florida</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/teenage-labor/amend-those.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brilliant Business Idea #6739</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/beer-train/beer-train.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/beer-train/beertrain.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>All aboard the beer train!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>On Jan 5 2019 I had a brilliant idea: a bar where the beer is served by trains on a model railroad.</p>
<p>Since then, I had not thought of this idea, until recently I was cleaning up the notes app in my phone. It seems as good of an idea today as it did 5 years ago.</p>
<p>So I looked it up, and what do you know, somebody beat me to the punch. In <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OKnjXgUcO4c">Prague</a>, it’s called Vytopna, and it’s seemingly a hit with the tourists. I see some <a href="https://www.947wls.com/2017/06/19/chicago-is-getting-its-own-beer-train-marshmallow-restaurant-and-more-divvy-bikes/">reports</a> that the small Czech chain was supposed to expand into America via Chicago, but from what I can tell those plans never materialized. I think the concept would do very well in this country, and would certainly patronize any establishment that took up the concept, at least once.</p>
<p>One of these days I’ll have an idea that isn’t already taken.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>business</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/beer-train/beer-train.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Year in Review 2023</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/review-2023/year-in-review-2023.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/review-2023/IMG_1806.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The Scott Monument in Edinburgh, captured on my honeymoon</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I got married, visited the ancestral homeland (Scotland), and attended my first in-person academic conference in years (NAAFE). 2023 was the year I felt the pandemic move firmly into the rear view. Hopefully going forward I will maintain that momentum, especially in regards to travel, as I feel I have a few lost years to make up for.</p>
<p>What else can I say about 2023?</p>
<p>I watched a lot of sports. The only time I really felt invested was during the FSU football season, which saw them go undefeated until a horrific bowl game loss to UGA yesterday. Everton is doing better than last year, except that they are still in the relegation zone due to the draconian points deduction. Honestly I have not even watched that much soccer, maybe as the campaign continues my interest will intensify, especially if Everton are once again fighting for safety.</p>
<p>Since I watched a lot of sports (besides soccer), I also watched a lot of commercials. I believe I am relatively pro-commercial, at least compared to most people I know. Yet I have numerous gripes with the commercials I see. First and foremost: there simply is not enough variety. I see the same commercials again over and over, and I simply do not understand the economics of how that, in the current year, is the equilibrium. If you spend time on YouTube, you will see a much greater variety of ads, often linked to the topic of the video you are watching. Yet when watching sports, I am expected to watch the same ads over and over, mostly from insurance companies. Who selects insurance coverage on any other basis than getting a large number of quotes and selecting the best rate? And why is Shaq the spokesman for everything from pizza to cheap cruise vacations to printer ink (also for Icy-Hot, but at least that one makes sense, it is the only ad in which he actually, you know, plays basketball). In 2024, I need MLB Network to get it together and run ads from more than 8 companies.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mma.prnewswire.com/media/2281632/PepsiCo_Shaq_I_Wish_Commercial.jpg?p=twitter" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>How many commercials can this guy do?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I digress.</p>
<p>2023 also brought a fair number of developments in the world of economics. Most notably, the US seems to have definitively achieved a “soft landing”: inflation has been driven down to manageable levels, with no recession in sight. Of course, don’t tell that to my mother, or vast numbers of other Americans, for whom I think the working definition of a recession is “a time in which myself and people I know are financially struggling”, which with elevated home prices, rents, and interest rates, encompasses a larger share of the population than the new phillips curve numbers would suggest.</p>
<p>Now about those home prices: is it a bubble? Most people in my profession seem to have come around to saying no. I was a bit of a holdout, and circa this Summer I thought the Case-Shiller index for some markets was showing signs of weakness, but the latest numbers do not bare that out. So seemingly, no, it is not a bubble, and yes, somehow, a 1000 sqft home older than my grandpa, in the neighborhood he grew up in, is now close to a half a million. I always thought Pinellas County was similar in its urban topography to Los Angeles, and now we are getting home prices to match. Here’s to remote work and telecommuting, and the flexibility it brings; with any luck 2024 may see me joining the hordes leaving their old familiar nests for cheaper pastures.</p>
<p>If we do decamp, I’ll need to find a place with a good sized backyard for my dog Cannoli. He’s getting older, and yet shows no signs of slowing down, except that he has firmly decided he does not like being picked up. I don’t know how we survived living in a 2nd floor apartment with him, at this point a fenced in backyard seems like an absolute must-have for him to run around. In a remarkable first, one of his Christmas 2022 gifts is going to survive into 2024, so perhaps he is learning to be more gentle. This year he got a gigantic buffalo horn, we will see how long that lasts, I give it 2 months tops.</p>
<p>I already made a post about my favorite music of the year, but I neglected to talk about my personal musical activities for the year. I adopted a new moniker, <a href="https://www.ebinlo.com">EBINLO</a>, and released a few pieces of music and some DJ mixes. Going forward I will keep posts about music stuff mostly segregated to the EBINLO blog, but will occasionally mention it here as well, especially if there are any major milestones to report. This year saw me acquire more gear than I ever have before, thanks to my decision to get into Eurorack. But I think it is working, the modular system keeps me motivated to create in a way that did not happen when working just in Ableton. In the back of my mind I always consider whether I should try to improve my piano skills as a way to improve my relationship with music-making, but probably I never will. I would say my biggest goal for music making in 2024 is to spend less time on sound design and more time on arrangement.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a0837383706_16.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>My newest track includes the unprecedented use of inhale-scream vocals, which I may expand on in the future</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I didn’t dance enough this year! Probably I could say that about almost any year, but I think this year it was especially true. It’s so important to move around, and there’s no better way to move than with the music. I think I remain firmly committed to spontaneous, unchoreographed dancing, and I wonder what the current dance floor situation is like in the age of the TikTok dances.</p>
<p>Even the wedding, unfortunately, involved less dancing than I would have liked. Though there was I suppose by most people’s standards plenty of dancing. The wedding was mostly as nice as we could have hoped, and in fact we achieved our stated goal of being legally bound to one another, which is the important part. The cake, I am told, was very good, though I only got a single bite of it. The family seemed to enjoy themselves, and we are all very grateful that the extensive planning and coordinating is now done with.</p>
<p>If I had to summarize I would say: wedding good, Scotland better, economy debatable.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>sports</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/review-2023/year-in-review-2023.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Music Wrap-up 2023</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/music-2023/music-2023.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I listened to a lot of interesting music in 2023, although most of it actually was not new music, but rather older music from different genres and scenes that I had not previously explored very much, such as IDM from artists like <a href="https://squarepusher.bandcamp.com/album/feed-me-weird-things-remastered">Squarepusher</a> and <a href="https://plaid.bandcamp.com/album/feorm-falorx">Plaid</a>, old techno released off the <a href="https://kompakt.fm">Kompakt</a> label, and instrumental funk from artists like <a href="https://thebudosband.bandcamp.com/album/the-budos-band">The Budos Band</a>. In any case, I’ll mostly focus this post on music that actually came out this year, of which I also listened to plenty.</p>
<section id="albums" class="level1">
<h1>Albums</h1>
<p>With no further ado, my AOTY:</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 350px; height: 470px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1793449465/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://islandman-feat-okaytemiz-and-muhlisberberolu.bandcamp.com/album/direct-to-disc-sessions">Direct-to-Disc Sessions by Islandman feat Okay Temiz and Muhlis Berberoğlu</a></iframe>
<p>I found this while browsing new releases from the Juno webshop, where the description caught my eye: “Future-folktronica at its very best.” I do not know any of these artists, and have not yet bothered to listen to any other releases from any of them, but this one-time collaboration is amazing. Danceable throughout, and unlike anything I’ve ever heard, I just can’t recommend it enough.</p>
<p>Other albums I can recommend include:</p>
<p>A fun bass album from Bristol-based duo Glume and Phossa.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1359512353/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://whitepeach.bandcamp.com/album/wprlp001-between-surface">WPRLP001 - Between Surface by Glume &amp; Phossa</a></iframe>
<p>A much-appreciated return to form from Fall Out Boy.</p>
<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/5rHd8n9uWIpq9w0PP5ZcI3?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="352" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>
<p>A big, danceable, electronic RnB/Pop album from Jessy Lanza off the <a href="https://hyperdub.net/en-us">Hyperdub</a> label.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3119055298/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://jessylanza.bandcamp.com/album/love-hallucination">Love Hallucination by Jessy Lanza</a></iframe>
<p>A modern trip-hop-inflected pop masterpiece from George Clanton:</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1059279715/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://georgeclanton.bandcamp.com/album/ooh-rap-i-ya">Ooh Rap I Ya by George Clanton</a></iframe>
<p>A wonderful genre-bending indie pop entry from German artist J Vague</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=376511840/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://jvague.bandcamp.com/album/silver">SILVER by J. Vague</a></iframe>
</section>
<section id="singles" class="level1">
<h1>Singles</h1>
<p>There were also a couple singles that stood out to me this year, even if I didn’t like the rest of the album enough to recommend the whole thing.</p>
<p>Going Home to a Party - JW Francis. Indie pop.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1053041854/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=994267083/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://jwfrancis.bandcamp.com/album/dream-house">Dream House by JW Francis</a></iframe>
<p>Not Worth Saving - Skyler Accord. Goth stuff.</p>
<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/42rmSRBeqfITaIpB7Ybcs0?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>
<p>Where the Weeds Don’t Grow - Zach Schimpf. Electronic indie pop.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2186672673/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=1029252354/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://zachschimpf.bandcamp.com/album/white-lightning">White Lightning by Zach Schimpf</a></iframe>
<p>Ghosting - Isolde Lasoen. Belgian indie pop.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3122961206/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=4104854908/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://isoldelasoen.bandcamp.com/album/oh-dear">Oh Dear by Isolde Lasoen</a></iframe>
<p>Runner - CARSICK. Pop-punk.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1718294732/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=1139781541/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://alcopop.bandcamp.com/album/drunk-hymns">Drunk Hymns by CARSICK</a></iframe>
</section>
<section id="dj-mixes" class="level1">
<h1>DJ Mixes</h1>
<p>I did not listen to many DJ mixes this year, but I can highly recommend this entry from the Fabric Presents series, in which Chaos in the CBD dig up a lot of great vintage house tunes.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 350px; height: 470px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1500360339/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/transparent=true/" seamless=""><a href="https://chaosinthecbd.bandcamp.com/album/fabric-presents-chaos-in-the-cbd">fabric presents Chaos In The CBD by Chaos In The CBD</a></iframe>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>AOTY</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/music-2023/music-2023.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New Florida Parks Resident Preference Policy</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/florida-parks-resident-preference/parks-preference.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently received an email from the Florida Department of Environmental Protection informing me that “Effective Jan.&nbsp;1, 2024, at noon Eastern time, only Florida residents may make reservations for cabins and RV, tent, boat and equestrian campsites 11 months in advance. Non-Florida residents will be able to make reservations 10 months in advance.”</p>
<p>This is the result of <a href="https://www.myfloridahouse.gov/Sections/Bills/billsdetail.aspx?BillId=76845&amp;SessionId=99#:~:text=CS%2FHB%20109%20%2D%20State%20Park%20Campsite%20Reservations&amp;text=State%20Park%20Campsite%20Reservations%3A%20Requires,specified%20information%20for%20advance%20reservations.">Florida 2023 HB 109</a>, signed into law back in May. I am not clear on whether I think this is a good or bad development. Selfishly speaking, it will make it slightly easier for me to get a booking at certain campsites, though I have not actually made such a booking since January 2022. On the other hand, I worry it may hurt our tourism industry. Thinking ahead, I also wonder whether similar laws being passed in other states could lead us to an unfortunate equilibrium where the best campsites in America are all for the exclusive use of in-state residents.</p>
<p>Regarding tourism impacts, I think it is worth noting that there has been some serious neglect in how this bill was handled in the state legislature: potential tourism impacts were declared to be essentially 0. In the legislature, bills undergo staff review, including an economic impact section, if you look at the links under the “staff analysis” section of the previous link, you can see that in 8 separate versions of the analysis of this bill, all declared that the impact of this bill on state and local government revenues would be none.</p>
<p>Let me say it is not obvious a priori whether this law would lead to a reduction or increase in sales tax revenues. That depends on a number of parameters, such as whether in-state residents or tourists tend to spend more on a given campsite trip, and whether tourists who are locked out of their preferred campsite due to the new rules subsequently cancel their trip entirely, or if they simply substitute to a different kind of trip, and if so how much money they spend on that substitute trip compared to their first choice trip. With those caveats in mind, and armed with 0 data on the question, let me say that my intuition is strongly that tourists tend to spend more than in-state residents, and that the new law will lead to a substantial reduction in tourist trips and consequently state sales tax revenues.</p>
<p>The fact that there is no amount of thought dedicated to this question in the official analysis of the law, and that the law still passed unanimously in both chambers, signals to me that in some cases the neurons simply are not firing in Tallahassee.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>outdoors</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>policy</category>
  <category>florida</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/florida-parks-resident-preference/parks-preference.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On The Shohei Deal</title>
  <dc:creator>Zander Gordan</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/on-shohei-deal/on-shohei-deal.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It is generally agreed that a dollar today is worth more than a dollar tomorrow. There are a number of reasons for this, the ones I would focus on are inflation, investments, and the value of spending money earlier in our life as opposed to when we are in our old age. Economists often speak of this idea by referring to the “time value of money.”</p>
<p>Given the last couple years of inflation we have experienced, I think everyone understands the time value of money in the sense that you could have bought more stuff for the same amount of money a few years ago than you could get now. But an even more fundamental aspect of the time value of money has to do with investment opportunities. If you can take your money and put it to productive use by running a business, or investing in someone elses business, then the profit that you generate while that business is running is the value created by having the money invested in the business. Thus even in an economy with little to no inflation, the time value of money means that a dollar today is worth more than a dollar tomorrow, because the dollar today can be invested to earn a financial return.</p>
<p>I want to talk about what the time value of money means for the recent deal bringing Shohei Ohtani across town to the LA Dodgers. The punchline is that what was initially announced as a $700 million, 10 year deal, is substantially less impressive than it sounds since the vast majority of the money will be received far in the future. Specifically, <a href="https://theathletic.com/5129506/2023/12/11/dodgers-shohei-ohtani-contract-deferrals/">we are now being told</a> that Shohei will receive only $2 million per year for the 10 years he plays under the new contract (2024-2033), and then will receive $68 million for ten years after (2034-2043). The Athletic article I link to above has this to say about the arrangement: “For the 10 years that he is to play for the Dodgers, then, Ohtani's deal could be thought of as being worth $46 million on average every year. But over the full 20-year lifespan of the deal — including the following 10 years when the deferrals are paid out, a time when Ohtani is no longer under contract with the team — he is to make a total of $700 million.”</p>
<p>I thought that this quote might be confusing to some baseball fans with limited economics and finance knowledge, which is the reason I wanted to make this post. Based on what I have written already, hopefully it is clear that the reason the deal can be thought of as only worth $46 million a year has to do with investments: Shohei would be much better off if they gave him the full $700 million immediately and then he could invest the money, or even if he was paid $70 million each year, as I initially thought when I first heard the news this weekend. But I want to provide some context about how exactly the $46 million figure was reached, and what it means for how you should think about this historic deal.</p>
<p>The $46 million figure quoted by The Athletic is what’s known in baseball as the average annual value (or AAV) of the contract, which may be a familiar term to baseball fans who follow the sport closely. In most contracts, the AAV is simply the average value of the contract, so a 2 year contract that paid $10 million in the first year and then $20 million in the second would have an AAV of $15 million. But the calculation becomes more complicated for the Shohei deal, because of the deferrals, or money that is paid after the year in which the player worked. In this case, the AAV is calculated using an economic concept known as Net Present Value (or NPV), which accounts for the time value of money.</p>
<p>NPV is defined as an amount of money that you could give someone right now, that would be equivalent to the cash flow received over time, given certain assumptions about how the money could be invested. Let me illustrate this with the simplest example possible: say that you have a high yield savings account that pays 10% interest per year, so if you put $100 in it on New Years Day, then at the end of the year you will have $110. In this case, if someone offers you a contract that pays out $110 at the end of the year, you would be just as well off going with a different contract that paid $100 at the start of the year. Even though the dollar value of one contract is higher, their NPV is the same due to the time value of money.</p>
<p>In baseball, the contracts are much more complex, and pay out different amounts of money over various time periods. Shohei’s deal is particularly complex because of the deferrals. But the core concept of NPV is the same when analyzing these contracts no matter how complex they are: the NPV of the contract is the amount that the player could be paid immediately, which would be worth the same as the money they receive over the course of the years of their contract, when we assume that the player could invest their money to earn a certain interest rate.</p>
<p>For those who like numbers and formulas, here is the formula for NPV (others can skip over this):</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0ANPV%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bt=0%7D%5ET%20%5Cfrac%7BP_t%7D%7B(1+r)%5Et%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_t"> is the payment in year <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r"> is the interest rate (10% or 0.1 in my earlier example). In year 0, when the contract begins, any money paid immediately is worth the full amount. But as the years go by, the money paid in future years is worth less in NPV terms because we forfeit the opportunity to invest and grow our money in the foregoing years.</p>
<iframe width="800" height="400" src="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vQhcp4ff0ZDxRh4BHrC5oQjfmB7UsQW8KfTajvwieJ1AeJ67GmTfbwqFeKYlLVDFxrS-F7_QwGGsC29/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;headers=false"></iframe>
<p>In the spreadsheet above, I show the calculations of NPV for the entire Shohei deal, as well as for the AAV calculation. Let’s break it down. Starting on the right side of the sheet, which shows the AAV calculation: Shohei will receive $2 million each year that he plays, then for 9 years after that will not receive any more compensation for that year of play, until finally after 10 years he receives the $68 million he is owed. Based on this schedule of payments, I use the <a href="https://support.google.com/docs/answer/3093184?hl=en">Google Sheets NPV function</a> to calculate an AAV of $44 million (I am not sure why I come to a slightly different value than The Athletic, but the figures are close enough). What you can not see in the spreadsheet is one crucial input to the NPV function, the interest rate. I have used an interest rate of 4.43%, and will discuss that choice of rate in a little bit.</p>
<p>Now on the left side of the sheet, I compare the “$700 million 10 year” Shohei deal under two different cash flow scenarios: Scenario B, where $70 million is paid each year for 10 years, AKA what I thought was happening when the deal was announced on Saturday, and Scenario A, the actual deal with heavy deferrals. I have calculated the NPV for both deals, which at a 4.43% interest rate is $365 million for Scenario A, and $555 for Scenario B. In other words, the NPV of the actual deal is only 66% of what I thought it was when the deal was initially announced. In the weeks leading up to the deal, I think many people were expecting something like 10 years $500 million with a conventional payment schedule, and so we can see that in NPV terms the actual deal was much closer to expectations. Still a historic deal, but not quite as record smashing as initially reported.</p>
<p>Now about that interest rate: I have used 4.43% because apparently this is the rate that MLB will use. Lone Star Ball <a href="https://www.lonestarball.com/2023/12/11/23996986/deferred-money-mlb-luxury-competitive-balance-tax-shohei-ohtani-los-angeles-dodgers-cba">has covered the issue well</a>, showing that in the collective bargaining agreement it is stated that the interest rate used for calculating NPV in AAV is the “Federal mid-term rate” as calculated by the IRS, which according to <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-drop/rr-23-18.pdf">this document</a> is 4.43%. Now is a good time to mention that the interest rate to use in these sorts of analyses is a very contentious issue. For instance, the US federal government recently announced that it would change the rate used in its analysis of federal regulations from a range of 3-7% to 2%, and this was <a href="https://www.epi.org/publication/epi-comment-re-proposed-omb-circular-no-a-4-regulatory-analysis/">widely commented on</a> by many economists and institutions and not without controversy. But even in lower stakes situations such as baseball, it is not always easy to know what rate to use. The problem is related to the concept of financial risk, as you can generally earn a higher interest rate if you are willing to make riskier investments. In essence, if the owners of the Dodgers are willing to take on the necessary risk to earn interest on their investments of greater than 4.43%, then this Shohei deal will mean that the $45 million AAV is a very good deal for them in terms of avoiding baseball’s Competitive Balance Tax.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>sports</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <guid>https://www.zandergordan.com/posts/on-shohei-deal/on-shohei-deal.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
